Okay, today's דף ל"ט *Daf Lamed Tes*, we pick up on ל"ח
עמוד ב' *Lamed Ches Amud Beis* with line תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan.
שור של ישראל *Tanu Rabbanan Shor Shel Yisrael*, line starts with the
word העמוני *Haamoni* about twenty lines from the bottom, and our learning
should be in the merit of the protection of our חיילים *Chayalim*
and חיילות *Chayalot* and the speedy return of all the hostages. Okay,
so we are continuing with the theme of the משנה mishna *Mishna*
that an ox of a Jew gores an ox of a non-Jew,
it is פטור patur, *patur*, but a non-Jew that gores the ox
of a Jew pays full damages, and obviously that's, you know, something
that's very challenging to explain as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* dealt with.
And now we're going to deal with the issue as it relates
to Samaritans. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן שור של ישראל שנגח
שור של כותי פטור, ושל כותי שנגח שור של ישראל, תם tam.
משלם חצי נזק, meshalem chatzi nezek. ומועד משלם נזק nezek שלם *Tanu
Rabbanan Shor shel Yisrael shenagah shor shel Kuti patur, veshel Kuti shenagah
shor shel Yisrael, Tam meshalem chatzi nezek, uMuad meshalem nezek shalem*. So
if an ox of a Jew gores an ox of a Samaritan,
it's exempt, and that, but if a Samaritan that gores our ox
has the normal payment of half for a תם tam? *Tam* and
full for a מועד muad. *Muad*. Now that does not seem to
make sense. The fact is it's not the law of a non-Jew.
If it was the law of a non-Jew, it would pay full
if it gored us, but it's paying the normal things if it
gores us, half or full based on תם tam? *Tam* or מועד
muad, *Muad*. So presumably it has the status of a Jew. So
why are we exempt when our ox gores theirs? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* never really looks at the position of the חכמים Chachamim?
*Chachamim*. It'll look at the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi
Meir* which we're about to cite, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות
Tosfos *Tosafot* both say that you know, presumably this is a קנס
knas *knas*, this is something that is done in order as the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will say by רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir*
in a second, in order to create separation between us and the
Samaritans. We should not have any, you know,
involvement
with them and leading to intermarrying with them and so on. Even
if they're הלכה halacha *halachically* Jews, we want to keep our distance
from them. They don't really keep, you know, they keep a whole
different, like they have a whole different type of way of practicing
the religion, so we want to keep our distance from them. So
therefore when our ox gores theirs, we don't pay. But when their
ox gores ours, we're not going to make them pay more than
they're obligated, actively take money from them, but we will have, so
therefore it's half and full based on תם tam? *Tam* and מועד
muad *Muad*. But when our ox gores theirs then there will be
some, you know, impunity and we won't have to pay and that
certainly will give them second-class status and create walls and barriers between
us and them. That's the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
אומר שור של ישראל שנגח שור של כותי פטור, ושל כותי שנגח
שור של ישראל, בין תם tam. בין מועד muad משלם נזק שלם
*Rebbi Meir Omer Shor shel Yisrael shenagah shor shel Kuti patur, veshel
Kuti shenagah shor shel Yisrael, bein Tam bein Muad meshalem nezek shalem*.
That if our ox gores theirs, exempt, like the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim*,
and theirs that gores ours, pays full, just like the law of
non-Jews. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks that this indicates for רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rebbi Meir* these Samaritans are non-Jews. למימרא דסבר רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir כותים Kutim גירי אריות הן *Lemeimra desavar Rebbi Meir
Kuti'im gerei arayos hen*. This indicates that רבי מאיר Rabi Meir *Rebbi
Meir* holds that Samaritans are converts due to the lions. What does
this mean? If you look at תנ"ך *Tanach* in מלכים ב' *Melachim
Beis* after the destruction of the first בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, excuse
me, נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar* comes and he takes different nations and he puts
them in the land of Israel, among them people from כותא *Kuta*,
so that's the Samaritans, and it says that they continued worshipping their
gods, but then God
in
the land, but God, you know, sent lions upon them and they
realized that they had to worship the true God. Okay, and so
therefore the question is, did they actually convert or not, or the
assumption is they did convert but was it a good conversion? Are
they
גירי אריות *gerei arayos*, converts of
lions, or
גירי אמת *gerei emes*, true converts? Now as תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* points
out, the accepted הלכה halakha *halacha* is that regardless of motivation, you
know, the conversion is good if the person at the end of
the day is sincere about their desire to convert, whatever their motivation
is. So everybody could agree that their motivation was they didn't want
the lions to attack them. The question is, at the end of
the day was their conversion sincere? That would be גירי אמת *gerei
emes*. Or was their conversion not sincere? And that would be גירי
אריות *gerei arayos*. So it seems that רבי מאיר Rabi Meir *Rebbi
Meir* holds that their conversion was not sincere and that they are
treated like non-Jews, they are non-Jews, and therefore that's why these הלכות
*halachos* of full payment applies to them. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, but so למימרא דסבר רבי מאיר Rabi Meir כותים Kutim גירי
אריות הן *lemeimra desavar Rebbi Meir Kuti'im gerei arayos hen*. ורמינהי *Verminhi*,
but I will challenge this. כל הכתמים הבאים מרקם טהורים *Kol haktzamim
habaim miRekem tehorin*. Any stains that are found on garments that come
from רקם *Rekem* are טהור tahor. *tahor*. What does this mean? A
woman who menstruates is a נדה *niddah*. If she has blood on
her garments, then rabbinically, since it didn't come directly from her body,
it's only rabbinically טמא tamei *tamei*, it's called a כתם *ketsem*. She's
טמא tamei *tamei* under certain circumstances and the garment and people who
touch the garment are טמא tamei *tamei*. Okay, so what if you
find a garment, a cloth, something on the street with a bloodstain?
So what's the story? So if it's in רקם *Rekem*, they're טהור
tahor. *tahor*. Why? Because the people living in רקם *Rekem* are non-Jews.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מטמא *Rebbi Yehuda metamei*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rebbi Yehuda* says no, it's טמא tamei *tamei* in רקם *Rekem*. מפני
שהן גרים וטועים *Mipnei shehein gerim veto'im*. They think they're non-Jews, but
they're actually converts and they're mistaken. converts from a long time ago
and they just have forgotten about that. So it is a bloodstain
from a Jew. Bloodstains of non-Jews are not מטמא. Okay, מבין הנכרים
טהורים mibien hanachrim tehorim
if you find it in places that it's clear that they're non-Jews
and obviously it's טהור. tahor? מבין
ישראל ומבין הכותים, mibien Yisrael umivein hakutim, if you find it from
among Jews or Samaritans, רבי מאיר מטמא, Rabbi Meir metamei, Rabbi Meir
says it's טמא tamei. because the blood of menstrual blood or the
stains from a woman's garments are טמא tamei. and כותים Kutim are
clearly according to this halachically Jews, right? And therefore their stains are
טמא as well. וחכמים מטהרים vechachamim metaharim and the וחכמים chachamim say
it's טהור. tahor, Why do they say it's טהור? שלא נחשדו על
כתמיהן. shelo necheshdu al kitmeihen.
Not because it's טהור, if you knew that it was on their
garments then yes it would be טמא and if it was found
in their house then it would be טמא. But if you're finding
something on the street then you have no idea what the source
of it was. Maybe the blood was from a chicken that was
slaughtered or something or from a bloody finger and we will assume
that they are very careful
about not letting their stained garments just be thrown out in public
and in the street. Okay, so that's their debate, whether we are
concerned about what the source of these stained garments are. But at
the end of the day it's clear that רבי מאיר and the
וחכמים chachamim agree that כותים are considered to be Jews. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, אלמא קסבר רבי מאיר כותים גירי אמת הן. alma
kasavar Rabbi Meir Kutim gerei emet hein. You see that רבי מאיר
holds that כותים are considered to be true Jews and therefore their
stains are טמא. So why is it that we don't pay them
and they pay us full? So אמר רבי אבא קנסו שקנס רבי
מאיר בממונם. amar Rabbi Abba knasu sheknas Rabbi Meir bemammonam. Rabbi Meir
is applying a קנס knas. to their money, meaning he's like freeing
us from paying them and demanding that they pay us full and
that way he's even more than the וחכמים. chachamim. שלא
יטמעו בהם, shelo yitame'u bahem, that we should not intermingle with them
and intermarry with them. Okay, because again, even though they are halachically
Jewish, they have a whole different set of practices and even to
some degree something
idolatrous came up, so we want to keep our distance from them.
Okay, so the basic difference between him and the וחכמים chachamim is
just that the וחכמים chachamim say don't pay, but we won't make
them pay us more than the law demands and רבי מאיר will
even make them pay us more than the law demands. מתיב רב
זירא, masiv Rav Zeira, Rav Zeira asks, ואלו נערות שיש להן קנס.
ve'eilu naaros sheyesh lahen knas. The following are the young נערות naaros
who you would pay a קנס. knas This is the תורה Torah
speaks about case of rape and seduction and paying 50 כסף kesef
and the man paying it. And the משנה mishna. says here
that these are the women that you pay to, meaning even the
following women: הבא
על הממזרת, haba al hamamzeres, a man who has sex with a
woman who's a ממזרת, mamzeret, even though halachically not allowed to marry,
the קנס knas still applies. ועל הנתינה, ve'al hanesina, who is, let's
say, it's a question exactly, but let's say it's somebody from the
Canaanite nations who was sort of put into slavery by King David.
But whatever, even if she converts and even if so marriage is
binding but you're not allowed to marry her. In that case, even
though you're not allowed to marry, halachically we're assuming she converted, so
therefore she's Jewish, so you would pay. ועל הכותית, ve'al hakutis, and
on the כותית, Kutit, again because they're Jewish. Okay, and סתם משנה
stam mishna is רבי מאיר. ואי סלקא דעתך קנסו שקנס רבי מאיר
בממונם, ve'isalka deitach knasu sheknas Rabbi Meir bemammonam, now if רבי מאיר
says that we're not going to make you pay them and we'll
make them pay you full and so on, so then הכא נמי
נקנוס hacha nami niknos כדי שלא יטמעו בהם, kedei shelo yitame'u bahem,
why not make a קנס knas? and say fine them by not
paying the קנס? knas Why not say the same way, you don't
have to pay when your ox gores, this man doesn't have to
pay when he has sex with
this כותית Kutit because really here,
it would be a way of in order to maintain separation. שלא
יטמעו בהם. shelo yitame'u bahem.
So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, what's the difference? No,
כדי שלא יהא חוטא נשכר. kedei shelo yehei chotei niskar. No, here
we're not going to say that because this man, there has to
be consequences for his actions. So that he should be able to
go ahead and rape and seduce this כותית Kutit and therefore not
have consequences for it, I mean oh my god that can lead
that just is will even tremendously exacerbate the type of that type
of unconscionable action. So therefore it's important that there be consequences and
that is more important than doing things to, in this case, make
sure they're sort of being treated in this second class status type
of way. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's for he is
going to pay like the normal הלכה would demand before you have
this principle of כדי שלא יטמעו. kedei shelo yitame'u. ונשקליה לעניים, venishkleia
la'aniyim, okay but why not make the man pay and there be
consequences but don't give it to them, give it to the poor?
So אמר רב מרי משום דהוי ממון שאין לו תובעין, amar Rav
Mari mishum dehavay mammon she'ein lo tve'in, because it's ממון mammon that
has nobody to sue for it. You know, the man can't pay
for his actions unless there's a plaintiff and somebody suing for it
in court. So who is going to demand that money? Nobody is
going to demand that money and therefore because no particular he
doesn't. So we allow it to still be that he pays to
the woman that he seduced or raped like the הלכה demands and
we do not treat it like the case of the ox where
we say no payment. Okay, so that's basically the end of that
issue about that imbalance of law between us and the non-Jews or
us and Samaritans. Now we get onto a new topic. Top of
ל"ט ע"א, lamed tet amud aleph, the משנה. mishna שור שפקח שנגח
שור שחרש שוטה וקטן חייב. shor she-piseach
she-nagach shor she-cheresh shoteh
ve-katan chayav.
If the ox of a פקח, piseach, normal person, gores the ox
of a חרש, cheresh, somebody who is a deaf-mute who is considered
to not have full intellect, or a שוטה, shoteh, somebody who has
mental illness, does not process reality normally like a schizophrenic, וקטן, ve-katan,
or a minor, all these three people are people that are not
held liable and responsible adults in court. So in that case, if
one of our oxes gores one of theirs, so we damage their
property, חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav. ושל חרש שוטה וקטן שנגח שור
שפקח פטור. ve-shel cheresh shoteh ve-katan she-nagach shor she-piseach patur. But if
one of their oxes gores the ox of somebody who's
a normal citizen... whatever, but just somebody who has his full mental
capacities and so on, in that case, פטור,
they're exempt because they are not held liable for their actions or
for their negligence. Okay, but that makes sense, but now we've got
a problem. Right, we've got this goring ox around and that's not
safe for this community. So what are we going to do? So
the משנה mishna continues. שור שחרש שוטה וקטן שנגח בית דין מעמידין
להן אפוטרופוס. shor she-cheresh shoteh ve-katan she-nagach beis din ma'amidin lahen apitropas.
If their ox gored, בית דין beis din assigns for them an
אפוטרופוס, apitropas, which is
like a custodian for
their responsible for a guardian of their estate, somebody who takes the
responsibility for their property. And therefore he is going to be assigned
the responsibility to watch this ox and make sure that it does
not go out and gore. Now the normal אפוטרופוס apitropas for would
be let's say for cases of orphans who are under age and
inherited an estate and there he's being assigned the job in order
to protect their interests. This is a slightly different type of an
אפוטרופוס. apitropas. It is somebody to ensure that protects society and making
sure that somebody is there to guard the ox and stop it
from going out and goring. ומעידין להן בפני אפוטרופוס, u-meidim lahen bifnei
apitropas, and you testify against them in the presence
against their ox in the presence of the אפוטרופוס, apitropas, so in
order to make the אפוטרופוס מועד apitropas muad if he gores three
times.
Now,
נתפקח החרש נשתפה השוטה והגדיל הקטן. nitpake'ach ha-cheresh nishtapeh ha-shoteh ve-higdil ha-katan.
If the
חרש cheresh got his hearing back and the שוטה shoteh got
his sanity back, became his mental
illness subsided, and
the קטן katan became an
adult. חזר לתמותו דברי רבי מאיר. chazar le-tumuso divrei Rabi Meir. So
רבי מאיר says that the ox now is considered to be a
תם. tam, Why is that? Even if he was warned three times
in the presence of the אפוטרופוס. apitropas. Well, let's see. רבי יוסי
אומר הרי הוא בחזקתו. Rabi Yosi omer harei hu ve-chez-kaso. No, it
remains a מועד. muad, So here it was warned in front of
the אפוטרופוס apitropas three times, became a מועד, muad. and then the
people that he was watching it for, the person, whether it was
a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, now became a responsible adult
and it goes back and it goes into their control.
So you understand the position of רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi that says
it remains a מועד muad. because you have a habitual
gorer. But why does רבי מאיר say it goes back to being
a תם? tam. So this is called in the גמרא רשות משנה.
gemara rishus meshaneh. Does the changing of possession change its status and
make its status revert back to a
תם? tam And one way simply to understand this issue of course
is whether it's ייעודי תורא yi'udei tora or ייעודי גברא. yi'udei gavra.
What's the purpose of warning three times? After warning three times it
shows that the ox is habitual. If it's to show ייעודי תורא,
yi'udei tora, if it's to show the ox is habitual, we've proven
the ox is habitual and now that it goes back into the
possession of the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan who are no
longer חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, anyway now that it goes
back changes possession, it remains habitual and the person will be liable
full damages. That would make sense, that's the position of
רבי יוסי. Rabi Yosi. רבי מאיר could be holding that it's ייעודי
גברא. yi'udei gavra. No, the reason you pay full is because you've
been warned three times and you've been negligent three times and now
you're going to start paying full. So that would apply to the
person who was warned, not to a new person. This could apply
in a lot of cases. You buy an ox that's already a
שור מועד, shor muad, does it go back to being a תם?
tam, You could also ask if you gave something to a שומר
shomer and then it became a מועד muad, and you took it
back. Although that could be considered one constant רשות rishus because there
a בן דעת ben da'as you give it to the שומר, shomer,
they represent you. Okay, so that's the debate of whether it goes
back to being a תם. tam. שור אצטדינין אינו חייב מיתה. shor
itztadinin eino chayav misa. A stadium ox is not חייב מיתה, chayav
misa, שנאמר כי יגח ולא שיגיחוהו. shenemar ki yigach velo she-yigichuhu. Because
meaning a stadium ox that was used in like these
games that they would have in the Roman, in the... and in
Rome and in the Roman stadiums, and they're like like a bullfights
and so on. Because here if it's being egged on to gore,
and it's not goring on its own, even if it kills somebody,
that does not it does not become a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal,
that's only if it gored on its own. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara
הגופא קשיא. Hagufe kasha. This is an internal contradiction. אמרת שור של
חרש שוטה וקטן שנגח שור של פקח פטור. Amarte shor she'cheresh shota
v'katan shenagach shor she'pikeach patur. You started by saying that when their
ox of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shota v'katan gores ours, you're
exempt. אלמא אין מעמידין אפוטרופוס לתם לגבות מגופו. Alman ein mimidin apitropus
l'tam ligbos migupo. Now obviously, you know, you don't have to say
that if they don't have an אפוטרופוס apitropus because obviously they're exempt,
they're exempt from everything, they're exempt when they themselves damage. It must
mean that even if you've appointed an אפוטרופוס, apitropus, as long as
the animal is still a תם, tam. you're not going to collect
from it. You might collect once it becomes a מועד, muad, but
not when it's a תם. tam. אין מעמידין אפוטרופוס לתם לגבות מגופו.
Ein mimidin apitropus l'tam ligbos migupo. You do not appoint an אפוטרופוס
apitropus for a תם tam. to enable you to collect from the
body of the תם, tam, meaning to collect from it as a
תם. tam, You can only the אפוטרופוס apitropus will only allow you
to collect as a מועד. muad, That's what's implied in the משנה
mishna because the משנה mishna. only starts, you know, talking about you
give העדאה ha'ada and you warn, or whatever, you'll be able to
start collecting once it's a מועד. muad. Okay, אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
let's look at the end of the משנה. mishna. שור של חרש
שוטה וקטן שנגח בית דין מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס ומעידין להם בפני האפוטרופוס.
Shor she'cheresh shota v'katan shenagach beis din ma'amidin lahem apitropus u'meidin lahem
bifnei ha'apitropus. If it gores, בית דין beis din assigns an אפוטרופוס
apitropus and testifies in front of the
אפוטרופוס. apitropus. אלמא מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס לתם לגבות מגופו. Alma ma'amidin lahem
apitropus l'tam ligbos migupo. That doesn't spell out when you start collecting,
even if it says you warn in front of them, so that
makes it sound like maybe you do start collecting when it's still
a תם. tam, Okay, so what's the story? אמר רבא הכי קתני.
Amar Rava hachi katani. Here's how you have to read it. אם
הוחזקו נגחנים, Im huchzeku nagchanim, if it has established itself as a
gorer. תוספות Tosafos points out that doesn't mean that it's done it
three times, but it just means that you can see that this
ox has a vicious nature and you know that you have to
act to protect the interests of society.
ואם הוחזקו נגחנים מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס, V'im huchzeku nagchanim ma'amidin lahem apitropus,
then you appoint an אפוטרופוס apitropus ומעידין בפני האפוטרופוס u'meidin bifnei ha'apitropus
ומשוינא ליה מועד u'mashvinan lei muad and then when you warn three
times in front of the אפוטרופוס apitropus and now it's a מועד,
muad. דכי הדר ונגח לשלם מעלייה. d'chi hadar v'nagach lishalem me'aliyah. Okay,
and then now when it gores, now that it's a מועד, muad,
now it'll pay out of pocket, not מגופו. migupo. Okay, and that
does sort of sound like it in the משנה. mishna The משנה
Mishnah. does sound like you're not going to start paying for this
until you've testified and until it becomes a מועד, muad not before.
Now רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say the גמרא Gemara never spells
out why you can't start paying when it's only a תם. tam,
And the basic answer, you know, is and they really struggle with
different reasons why that might be, but the basic answer is look,
the תורה Torah goes easy on a תם. tam Either the whole
thing is a קנס knas, and you really should be paying nothing
and therefore, you know, we'll go easy on the חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shota v'katan and not make them pay if the תורה, Torah,
you know, pay a קנס, if it's not a real liability. Or
you could say it the other way: it is a liability, but
because it's the first three times, the תורה, Torah, you know, went
easy on the person. So if the תורה Torah went easy on
the person and now we're dealing with חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shota
v'katan, we're going to go easy on them as well. So the
basic point is half payment clearly shows it's not normal תשלומין tashlumim
and therefore we're going to go easy on the חרש שוטה וקטן.
cheresh shota v'katan. We don't do it when it's a תם, tam,
but we will start paying once it becomes a מועד. muad So
you appoint this שומר shomer in order to help protect society and
there will start being payments once it becomes a מועד. muad. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says מעליית מאן? Me'aliyas man? Who pays for
it when it actually, whose property does it come out from, when
it actually, you know, goes out and gores after three times?
רבי יוחנן אמר מעליית יתומים. Rabbi Yochanan amar me'aliyas yesomim. The orphans
pay. Now they didn't do anything wrong. Now by the way, you
know, who is talking about orphans? We're talking about חרש שוטה וקטן.
cheresh shota v'katan. But when we talk about אפוטרופוס, apitropus, אפוטרופוס apitropus
normally is in the context of orphans, people who inherit property when
they're minors. So, you know, so that's sort of how it's being
framed. But it would be יתומים yesomim meaning minors that now have
this ox, and that's the case. Okay, so yes, they pay. Now
why should they pay? They're minors, they don't have any liability. So
we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara רבי יוסי בר חנינא
אמר מעליית אפוטרופוס. Rabbi Yose bar Chanina amar me'aliyas apitropus. No, the
אפוטרופוס apitropus was the one who was negligent, so he's the one
who pays. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi?
Did Rabbi Yochanan really say that it's the minors or the orphans
who pay? והאמר רבי יהודה אמר רב אסי אין נזקקין לנכסי יתומים
אלא אם כן ריבית אוכלת בהם. V'amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav Assi
ein nizkakim l'nichsei yesomim ella im ken ribis ocheles bahem. That when
you have minors, you do not, you know, and people come and
creditors come and want to collect from the estate that, you know,
that their father, whatever, left to them, that you don't allow any
of the court cases to proceed until they become adults. The only
exception that you make is is that if it's a non-Jew who
has loaned out, you know, that and the father borrowed money and
he's paying interest, then you go ahead and you deal with that
because you don't want to keep. having to having to having the
interest accrue. Okay. But basically you protect the orphans, you know, while
they're still minors and you don't and you don't process and you
don't deal with any sort of claims against their estate,
you know, they'll have to deal with it once they become adults.
רבי יוחנן אמר או חוץ מהא דהוא ריבית, Rabbi Yochanan amar o
chutz me'ha d'hu ribbis, I mean that case you just mentioned of
ריבית ribbis of interest, או כתובת אשה משום מזוני o kesubas isha
mishum mezoni or if the widowed wife of their father, you know,
she gets a right to be supported by the estate for her
room and board until her כתובה's kesuba paid out. So that's a
similar type of an example where they're incurring an ongoing loss paying
for her room and board, you know, so better just do the
lump sum payment of the כתובה kesuba and ultimately that will protect
their property. But other than these cases where you're allowing them to
pay to protect them from ongoing loss, you do not take anything
from the orphans while they are still orphans. So how could, so
if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that, how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan here say that it's going you're going to pay from the
property of the orphans? So איפכא, aipach, so the גמרא Gemara says
fine, reverse it. רבי יוחנן אמר מעליות אפוטרופוס, Rabbi Yochanan amar m'alyos
apotropis, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan will be the one that says that
the אפוטרופוס apotropis pays, רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר מעליות יתומים, Rabbi
Yosi bar Chanina amar m'alyos yesomim, it's from the יתומים's yesomim property
that that gets paid. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא משום
דקשיא ליה רבי יוחנן דרבי יוחנן מוקמת ליה לרבי יוסי בר חנינא
טועה, amar Rava mishum d'kashya leh Rabbi Yochanan d'Rabbi Yochanan mokmas leh
l'Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina toeh, because you had a problem that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan seemed to be inconsistent, in one case he says
you don't collect from orphans and here he says you do collect
from orphans, you're going to turn רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yosi
bar Chanina into an erring position? You're going to make him to
be the one that says you collect from orphans? We've already established
that you don't collect from orphans. So you moved רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan away from that position and now you put רבי יוסי בר
חנינא. Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina. So now he's holding this position which
you said is basically
one that there's a consensus that orphans don't pay. So you can't
do that to רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina, stick
him with that position. והא רבי יוסי בר חנינא דיינא הוא ונחית
לעומקא דדינא. V'ha Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina dayna hu v'nachis l'umka d'dina.
He's the judge
and he gets to the heart, the, you know, the depth of
the דין din and therefore you know he would never say that
you make the orphans pay if the general rule is orphans don't
pay. Okay, but somebody's gotta say it. And what's the logic if
that's the general rule? So let's take a look. אלא לעולם לא
תיפוך. Ela l'olam lo saipoch. Fine, don't reverse it. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says the orphans pay even though normally רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
protects the property of the orphans while they're still minors. How is
this case different? ומזיק שאני. u'mazik shani. So and it's different when
you know they went out and their ox damaged something. It's not
like some debt that they owe. All right, so that's a different
case. You know, there's a case where he will concede that they
do pay and the גמרא Gemara actually goes on, let's keep on
reading. לעולם לא תיפוך ומזיק שאני. L'olam lo saipoch u'mazik shani. רבי
יוחנן אמר מעליות יתומים Rabbi Yochanan amar m'alyos yesomim and now we're
going to spell it out. Not just they hurt somebody so they
have to pay for it, but no, מעליות
יתומים m'alyos yesomim why? אי אמרת מעליות אפוטרופוס, Ei amart m'alyos apotropis,
top of ל"ט עמוד ב', lamed tes amud bais, ממנע ולא עביד,
mimna v'lo avid,
he'll refuse to do it. Okay, now the interesting thing is it
does not seem that these אפוטרופוס apotropis would ever get any fee
for their efforts and for their labor.
And so therefore if, now what they would get is some status,
בית דין beis din trusts them to oversee and protect the property
of the orphans, okay. So it says here, but you know so
they're not going to be willing to take this position if they're
going to have to be paying out of pocket. They'll do their
best to not be negligent and so on, but if something happens,
you know it's going to be paid from the orphans. And since
we need to do this, we need somebody to watch it, we'll
have to make an exception to our rule and we'll have to
allow it to be the payment to come from the orphans or
we won't get anybody to watch it. רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר
מעליות אפוטרופוס, Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina amar m'alyos apotropis, and רבי יוסי
בר חנינא Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina says no, no, no, you do
pay from the אפוטרופוס, apotropis, you start by paying from the אפוטרופוס
apotropis when the initial נזק happens, the, you know, you still protect
the orphans while they're still minors and he goes to his bank
account and he pays. How about the fact that that will be
a disincentive for him to take this position? וחוזר ונפרע מן היתומים
לכשיגדלו V'chozer v'nifra min hayesomim l'chsheyigdelu and then and you and you
go ahead and when the orphans become adults then they'll pay for
it, okay, but they'll pay him back. So everybody agrees that in
order to get somebody to take this you know thankless job you
can't you have to exempt him from personal liability. And therefore eventually
the orphans are going to pay. The debate is whether the orphans
pay now, which רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even though normally he
agrees you don't take anything from the orphans while they're minors, or
whether the אפוטרופוס apotropis pays now and he'll collect later when they
become adults. Okay, but that is at least you know the position
here. Now תוספות Tosafot, points out that it sounds like from this
reason even from this גמרא Gemara that in order to get people
to take this position we have to exempt them from an אפוטרופוס
apotropis from any negligence. That goes against another גמרא Gemara that says
an אפוטרופוס apotropis is responsible. and he's negligent. And תוספות Tosfot makes
a distinction between two types of אפוטרופוס. apitropus. He says an אפוטרופוס,
apitropus, here the אפוטרופוס apitropus is doing a service for the community.
Okay, he's not really being trusted to handle the property of the
orphans. There's no real trust; he's just sort of like a policeman.
He's there to make sure the ox doesn't gore—that is not a
high-status role. And to get him to take that role, you have
to exempt him from payment. However, to put him in charge and
to trust him enough to oversee, you know, the estate of the
orphans, that is something that has a lot of status with it
and he might reap benefits in other ways that other people will
trust him, and therefore in that type of role, says תוספות, he
is liable for negligence. Okay, so that's the משנה. Mishnah The ox
does not pay as a תם, tam. the אפוטרופוס apitropus but there
is an אפוטרופוס apitropus but exemption of payment for a תם, tam,
but there is an אפוטרופוס apitropus to protect the community. You make
him a מועד, muad. after he's a מועד muad. there is payment
eventually that will come from the from the orphans even though it's
the אפוטרופוס apitropus who is negligent which is allowing it, you know,
to happen. Okay. And now the גמרא Gemara continues. ומעמידין להם אפוטרופוס
לתם לגבות מגופו תנאי. umaamidim lahem apitropus l'tam ligvos migufo tanai.
This question of does the אפוטרופוס apitropus when you make an אפוטרופוס
apitropus for this goring ox will it allow you to collect from
the from the animal even as a תם, tam that even though
we said that our משנה Mishnah says no, that actually is a
debate of תנאים. Tanaim. דתניא, Dtanya, we taught in the ברייתא: Beraita:
שור שנחרשו בעליו ושנשתטו בעליו והלכו בעליו למדינת הים. Shor shenitcharshu baalav
v'shenishtatshu baalav v'halku baalav limdinas hayam. An ox that the owners became
חרש cheresh or they became שוטה shoteh or they just abandoned their
property and they went over to מדינת הים Medinas Hayam and they
didn't assign anybody to watch it and protect it. Okay, so יהודה
בן נקוסא Yehuda ben Nekusa
אמר סומכוס amar Shumchus או, o,
so יהודה בן נקוסא Yehuda ben Nekusa says in the name of
סומכוס: Shumchus: הרי הוא בתמותו עד שיעידו בו בפני הבעלים. Harei hu
b'tamuso ad sheyoidu bo bifnei habaalim. It remains a תם tam until
it is testified in front of the owners. וחכמים אומרים: Vachachamim omrim:
מעמידין להם אפוטרופוס ומעידין להם בפני אפוטרופוס. maamidim lahem apitropus v'me'idim lahem
bifnei apitropus. That no, you assign an אפוטרופוס apitropus and you allow
that it to become a מועד muad, through warning the אפוטרופוס. apitropus.
So that sounds like they're debating whether you assign an אפוטרופוס apitropus
or not. Okay, but let's continue. נתפקח החרש נשתפה השוטה והגדיל הקטן,
Nitpakeiach hacheresh nishtafa hashoteh v'higdil hakatan,
let's say the חרש cheresh now got his hearing back and the
שוטה shoteh now became better from his mental illness and the minor
became an adult, ובא בעל ממדינת הים, uba baal m'medinas hayam, and
the owners returned from overseas, יהודה בן נקוסא Yehuda ben Nekusa אומר
סומכוס omer Shumchus so now in the name of סומכוס Shumchus he
says: חזר לתמותו. Chazar l'tamuso. It returns to being a תם, tam,
עד שיעידו בו בפני בעלים ad sheyoidu bo bifnei baalim until it's
warned in terms of you know directly to the owners, the original
owners who took it back. Okay, so this is the principle we
saw in the משנה mishnah of רשות משנה, reshus meshaneh, right, they
took it back it goes back to being a תם. tam. But
as the גמרא is going to say, so it sounds like they
agree that there was an אפוטרופוס apitropus to make it into a
מועד. muad. In order to say that it reverts to being a
תם, tam? you have to have agreed that there was a process
that made it a מועד. muad. So ורבי יוסי אומר הרי הוא
בחזקתו v'Rabbi Yosi omer harei hu b'chezskaso it remains a מועד. muad,
Okay, so the second debate is clear. There was an אפוטרופוס, apitropus,
it was made a מועד, muad, it now they become, you know,
responsible adults, it goes to them, does it go back to being
a תם tam, or does it stay a מועד. muad, But what's
the first debate? So let's take a look. אמרו מאי הרי הוא
בתמותו דקאמר סומכוס. Amru mai harei hu b'tamuso d'ka'amar Shumchus. When the
in the first case, you know, when the when סומכוס Shumchus said
it's it remains תם tam, and they said no you assign an
אפוטרופוס, apitropus, what's the debate? It's clear they both agree you assign
an אפוטרופוס apitropus and make it a מועד. muad So אילימא דלא
מעיד כלל, ileima d'lo m'id kelal, if if סומכוס Shumchus is saying
you do not have an אפוטרופוס apitropus and you don't make it
a מועד, muad, הא מדקתני סיפא חזר לתמותו, ha mi d'ktani seifa
chazar l'tamuso, since the end says that when they become, you know,
of well mind and adults they take possession and it reverts to
being a
תם, tam מכלל דאעיד mikhlal d'aid you see that סומכוס Shumchus agrees
that there was a process to make it a מועד, muad right,
because then because because only then he says and now it will
go back to being a תם. tam So if he agrees there's
a process of making it a מועד, muad, what is he debating
with the חכמים? Very good question. אלא מאי הרי הוא בתמותו, Ella
mai harei hu b'tamuso, what does סומכוס Shumchus mean that it remains
a תם? tam. הרי הוא בתמימותו, Harei hu b'tmimuso, it doesn't exactly
mean it remains a תם, tam it means it remains complete, דלא
מחסרינא ליה. d'lo mechasrina lei. He says I agree you will make
an אפוטרופוס apitropus and it can become a מועד muad, and pay
as a מועד, muad. and when that if they get better or
become an adult or whatever it'll go back to being a תם,
tam. but what but in the process of becoming a מועד muad
while it's still a תם tam הרי הוא בתמימותו harei hu b'tmimuso
it remains a pure תם tam meaning it is full and complete
and you don't have to pay during that period of time. Okay,
דלא מחסרינא ליה, d'lo mechasrina lei, you do not take away from
it, it's not going to pay from its body and it's not
like the laws of a תם. tam, אלמא אין מעמידין אפוטרופוס לתם
לגבות מגופו. Alma ein maamidim apitropus l'tam ligvos migufo. You although you
have an אפוטרופוס apitropus to make it into a מועד, muad the
אפוטרופוס apitropus does not allow you to collect from the body of
the תם tam. and pay as a תם. tam,
וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim, the חכמים say מעמידין לאפוטרופוס וממנין בפני אפוטרופוס,
maminim l'apitropas u-minnim bifnei apitropas, you assign an אפוטרופוס apitropas and that
means here although they don't say it, it's not clear. But אלמא
alma מעמידין אפוטרופוס לתם לגבות מגופו, maminim apitropas letam ligvos migufo, you
do make it pay from the body. Okay, so now we're having
our משנה mishnah that says that it's understood to be you don't
pay as a תם tam to be סומכוס, Sumchus, and reading into
the חכמים to say you do pay as a תם tam with
this אפוטרופוס. apitropas. Again, it's all very vague, none of this has
been spelled out neither in the משנה mishnah, or in this ברייתא,
braisa, but that's what we are saying. Okay. Now, מגופו. migufo.
וסיפא במאי קמיפלגי? Ve-seifa be-mai kamiflagi? What do they debate in the
end? You could also say in our משנה, what's the debate when
the minor becomes an adult and you know, the חרש cheresh becomes
hearing and so on and it goes back into their possession. So
what's that? The debate?
רשות משנה איכא בינייהו, Reshus meshaneh ika beineiyhu, whether changing possession, whether
the changing of the possession of ownership makes it go back to
its original status. סומכוס סבר רשות משנה, Sumchus savar reshus meshaneh, that
it does change its status and it goes back, ורבי יוסי סבר
רשות אינה משנה, ve-Rabbi Yossi savar reshus einah meshaneh, it doesn't make
a difference. And again, it's easy to think of this as a
question about whether the focus is on the owner or on the
ox, but the גמרא does not exactly tie it into that debate.
Okay. Let's take a look at another debate. תנו רבנן. שור חרש
שוטה וקטן שנגח. Shor cheresh shoteh ve-katan she-nagach. You have the ox
of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan that gored. רבי יעקב
משלם חצי נזק. Rabbi Yaakov meshalem chatzi nezek. Rabbi Yaakov pays half
damages. So this is very funny. The גמרא says, רבי יעקב מאי
עבידתיה? Rabbi Yaakov mai avidteih? What did רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov do
wrong that he's paying half damages? רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov pays half
damages. Okay, we're going to get רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov to pay.
אלא אימא רבי יעקב אומר משלם חצי נזק. Ella eima Rabbi Yaakov
omer meshalem chatzi nezek. Okay, רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says you pay
half damages, which is clearly what it meant, but it was pretty
funny. Okay. So now you have an idea of paying half damages
of an ox of חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve-katan. So what's
going on? So the גמרא says, במאי עסקינן? be-mai askinan? What's the
case? אי בתם פשיטא דכולי עלמא נמי חצי נזק הוא דמשלם. Ei
be-tam peshita de-kuly alma nami chatzi nezek hu de-meshalem. If it's a
תם, tam, obviously that you pay a half. Everybody agrees you pay
half. Now, the חידוש chiddush could be like we're saying that even
though it's חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, there was an אפוטרופוס
apitropas and you'll pay half even though it's a תם. tam We
saw that that was heavily debated. But רש"י ותוספות Rashi ve-Tosafot both
say then just say חייב. chayav. If all he's saying is that
you have an ox of a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan
that gores as a תם, tam you're חייב chayav because there's an
אפוטרופוס, apitropas, say חייב. chayav. By saying you pay חצי נזק chatzi
nezek suggests that it was possible to think that you would pay
full and he's saying you only pay חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. So
let's take a look.
So if it's a case of a תם tam and you're paying
because of אפוטרופוס, apitropas, what's the חידוש chiddush of חצי נזק? chatzi
nezek? Just say חייב. chayav. So אי בתם פשיטא דכולי עלמא נמי
חצי נזק הוא דמשלם. ei be-tam peshita de-kuly alma nami chatzi nezek
hu de-meshalem. Of course that's what you pay for תם tam, is
חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. So just say חייב. chayav. ואי במועד, Ve-ei
be-muad, if it's a case of a מועד, muad אי עביד ליה
שמירה, ei avid leih shemirah, if it was watched, כלל כלל לא
בעי לשלומי, kelal kelal lo ba'ei leshalumei, you shouldn't have to pay
at all. ואי לא עביד ליה שמירה, ve-ei lo avid leih shemirah,
and if it wasn't watched properly, כולי נזק בעי לשלומי, kuly nezek
ba'ei leshalumei, you should have to pay full. So what's the case
of paying half? Okay, so where you might have thought you paid
full, that's what it's reading into the words משלם חצי נזק. chatzi
nezek.
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, לעולם במועד, le-olam be-muad,
it is a מועד. muad? והכא במאי עסקינן דעבד ליה שמירה פחותה
ולא עבד ליה שמירה מעולה. Ve-hacha be-mai askinan de-avad leih shemirah pechusah
ve-lo avad leih shemirah me'ulah. You did a grade B שמירה shemirah
and not a grade A שמירה. shemirah. Okay? רבי יעקב סבר לה
כרבי יהודה דאמר צד תמות במקומה עומדת. Rabbi Yaakov savar lah ke-Rabbi
Yehuda de-amar tzad tamus bi-mekomah omedes.
He holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says an ox even
after it's become a מועד muad is really seen of as half
מועד muad. and half תם, tam and וסבר
לה כרבי יהודה ve-savar lah ke-Rabbi Yehuda and
holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda דאמר מועד סגי ליה בשמירה פחותה
de-amar muad sagi leih be-shemirah pechusah that a מועד muad B-level שמירה
shemirah is good. Only a תם tam needs A-level שמירה. shemirah. Okay.
So let's just pause there for a moment. That's a lot of
things. All right. So there's a whole debate later what level of
שמירה shemirah is needed to be exempt for the goring of an
ox and is it the same for a תם tam and a
מועד? muad. Now, you would think that because a תם tam you
pay half, there's less liability, you would need equal or less שמירה
shemirah to be exempt for a תם, tam and that is obviously
a very logical position. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda takes the counter-intuitive
position, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that a מועד muad, B-level
שמירה shemirah is enough as long as you're not negligent, even though
the ox has gored three times, as long as you're not grossly
negligent you're exempt. Okay. But for a תם tam you have to
do A-level שמירה shemirah to be exempt. Very bizarre. One way to
understand it is, well look, by a תם tam. you were never
negligent at all and the תורה Torah is making you pay. So
the תורה Torah is making you pay not because of any fault
of your own. So in order to be exempt, you need to
do excellent שמירה shemirah and it's seen as an act of God
that it's seen as completely separate from you. But whatever the case
might be, he has this counter-intuitive position that you need A-level שמירה
shemirah to be exempt from a תם tam. but only B-level שמירה
shemirah to be exempt from paying for a מועד. muad Now, you
also hold like the position of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you know
that a צד תמות במקומו עומדת, tzad tamus bimkomo omedes,
that an animal that becomes a מועד muad, is a half תם
tam half מועד. muad So you have this animal that's been warned
three times, half תם tam half מועד, muad and you did a
B-level שמירה. shmira. The B-level שמירה shmira means oh, so for the
מועד of it, you've done a sufficient שמירה shmira and you're exempt,
but for the תם tam of it, you have not done a
sufficient שמירה shmira because that needs A-level and you only did B-level,
and therefore you're going to remain חייב chayav for the תם. So
that's why he says you're חייב, chayav, but he says חצי נזק.
chatzi nezek. You might think you're חייב chayav full? No, because I
see this as a hybrid animal and because you did a B-level
שמירה, shmira, you're only going to be חייב chayav for the half
that's a תם. Okay, and of course now we have to say
the other חידוש chiddush that you pay for a תם even though
it's a חרש שוטה
וקטן.
cheresh shoteh
vekatan. צד תם במקומו עומדת, tzad tam bimkomo omedet, וסבר לה כרבי
יהודה, vesavar lah keRabbi Yehuda, and he also holds like רבי יהודה
דאמר מועד סגי ליה, de'amar muad sagi lei, oh, he just did
it, a צריכותא, tzrichuta, וסבר לה כרבנן, vesavar lah kerabbanan, he holds
like the Rabbis דאמרי מעמידין אפוטרופוס לתם לגבות מגופו. de'amri ma'amidin apitropus
letam ligvot migufo. So that's why he says you pay חצי נזק.
chatzi nezek He could have just said it's a תם and you
pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek, because, you know, מעמידין אפוטרופוס, ma'amidin apitropus,
but again, רש"י and תוספות say the גמרא assumes because he didn't
just say חייב, chayav, he said חצי נזק, chatzi nezek. it meant
you would have thought you pay full, but you're only paying half.
Why? It's a מועד, but it's a hybrid מועד תם, muad tam,
that's what רבי יהודה thinks that a מועד is, and B-level שמירה
shmira gets you off on the מועד but you're still paying for
the תם part and that's why you pay חצי נזק. Okay, we
will stop here.